### Yen-Hsun Lin

#### Résumé

Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica No. 128, Section 2 Academia Road Nangang District, Taipei City, 115, Taiwan

yenhsun@phys.ncku.edu.tw

+886-2-2789 8387

**1** 0000-0001-7911-7591

yenhsunlin.github.io

## Summary of Research

I am an astroparticle physicist with expertise in multimessenger astronomy and dark matter (DM) detection. My research focuses on three key areas: (1) supernova-neutrino-boosted DM, (2) anomaly heating from DM in compact stars, and (3) probing DM self-interactions and DM-nucleon interactions in stars and planets. The first area is particularly vital as it opens the new possibility for direct DM mass measurements using time-of-flight techniques. I also collaborate with DUNE/COHERENT members and work on reducing systematic uncertainties in DUNE-like detectors. Additionally, I contributed to the JUNO collaboration, assessing its data analysis to solar-captured DM. My background in astroparticle physics and extensive research experience have provided me with a deep understanding of DM and its broader implications to our Universe.

#### Topic of Interest

Astroparticle physics, dark matter physics, supernova and compact star physics, high performance computation, Bayesian inference, and Monte Carlo simulation.

#### **Programming**

Python, Cython, C++, Mathematica and Matlab.

## **Education**

National Chiao Tung University

Aug 2011 Jul 2016

PhD of the Institute of Physics

Aug. 2011 – Jul. 2016

Hsinchu, Taiwan

Thesis: Indirect detection of dark matter through neutrinos

Advisor: Prof. Guey-Lin Lin

National Chiao Tung University

Hsinchu, Taiwan

Master of the Institute of Physics (direct to PhD program)

Aug. 2010 – Jul. 2011

Advisor: Prof. Guey-Lin Lin

National Chiao Tung University

Hsinchu, Taiwan

Bachelor of the Department of Electrophysics

Aug. 2006 - Jul. 2010

# Experience

Postdoctoral Scholar
Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica
Aug. 2023 – Present

Host: Dr. Meng-Ru Wu

Visiting Scholar Melbourne, Australia
School of Physics, Melbourne University Oct. 2023 – Nov. 2023

Host: Prof. Nicole F. Bell

Postdoctoral Scholar

Physics Division, National Center for Theoretical Sciences

Taipei, Taiwan

Dec. 2021 – Jul. 2023

Distinguished Postdoctoral Scholar
Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica
Taipei, Taiwan
Aug. 2019 – Dec. 2021

**Host:** Dr. Meng-Ru Wu

Postdoctoral Researcher

Tainan, Taiwan

Department of Physics, National Cheng Kung University

Oct. 2017 – Jul. 2019

Host: Prof. Chuan-Hung Chen

### Honors & Awards

1. NCTS Postdoc Paper Award

Awarded by the Physics Division, National Center for Theoretical Sciences (NCTS).

2. Best Research Paper Award for Junior Research Investigator
Awarded by the Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica.

Taiwan, 2024

3. Selected Participant of the 13<sup>th</sup> HOPE Meeting with Nobel Laureates
Representative of Taiwan.

Japan, 2022

4. Distinguished Postdoctoral Scholar
Independent position with grant, selected by the Academia Sinica.

Taiwan, 2019

5. **Annual Best PhD Thesis in Physical Science**Best PhD Thesis of the year, awarded by the Taiwan Physical Society.

Taiwan, 2017

6. Selected Honorary Member of the Phi Tau Phi Scholastic Society
Issued to the student graduated with top score.

Taiwan, 2016

# Github Repository

• snorer: Spernova-Neutrino-bOosted daRk mattER

**Description:** Evaluating the time-of-flight signatures of boosted dark matter due to supernova neutrinos from Milky Way, SN1987a and arbitrary distant galaxy.

Role: Main developer and maintainer

Project Page: https://github.com/yenhsunlin/snorer

ullet dukes: DiffUse-boosted darK mattEr by Supernova neutrinos

**Description:** Evaluating the signatures of diffuse boosted dark matter by supernova neutrinos

in the early Universe.

Role: Main developer and maintainer

Project Page: https://github.com/yenhsunlin/dukes

ullet dynesor: DY namical NEsted S ampling integrat OR

Description: MCMC integrator for evaluating multidimensional integration based on dynam-

ical nested sampling.

Role: Main developer and maintainer

Project Page: Non-disclose.

# Scientific Activities & Services

#### Collaboration membership

1. With Members of DUNE/COHERENT Collaborations

U.S.A.

♦ Collaborating with Dr. Gianluca Petrillo and Dr. Yun-Tse Tsai

2020 - Present

- $\diamond$  Analysis the impact due to  $\nu_e$ -Ar cross section uncertainty
- ♦ Improving pinched parameter sensitivity via Machine Learning

2. Jiangmen Underground Neutrino Observatory (JUNO)

Jiangmen, China

2015 - 2016

Co-author of the JUNO Yellow Book (R&D tech notes)
 Sensitivity projection for the solar-captured DM in JUNO

### Workshop organization

• Organizer of the Mini-workshop on Novel Experimental and Astrophysical Probes for Dark Matter, Taipei, Taiwan, 2021

#### Journal referee

- 1. Physical Letter B
- 2. Annals of Physics